[SPEAKER_01]: So, this is a question from a friend who is suffering from fear.
[SPEAKER_01]: He says, I constantly think about all the ways I could suffer in the future and try to put things in place to prevent those future sufferings.
[SPEAKER_01]: But no matter what I do, I can't eliminate uncertainty or control every possible danger.
[SPEAKER_01]: How do I stop my mind from endlessly trying?
[SPEAKER_01]: How can I learn to accept the unknown?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, the result... well, all of that which is described is really a result of the mind that's still not under your control.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you can't... you can't teach your mind, you can't tame your mind simply by wishing it stops and trying to get rid of the things that bother it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You need to start training it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then you have to start looking into why is my mind
[SPEAKER_00]: Still not pliable, as the suttas would say.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why is it still not listening to me?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why does it still revolve around the same fearful scenarios?
[SPEAKER_00]: And, like, what is it that I'm doing that's enabling it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because usually people would like to have the view... well, not to have a view, but they would like to be able to go through day-to-day life simply
[SPEAKER_00]: Not having to think about these things, unless they come up.
[SPEAKER_00]: Unpleasant things, like fear, anxiety, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: And when they do come up, then they want to be able to not think about them, per will.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, oh, I just wish this goes away.
[SPEAKER_00]: Mine would only stop thinking about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But mine thinking about those fearful aspects, and so on, it's... that's not the problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's just the symptom of an underlying problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's just showing you that the problem is elsewhere, and you're not addressing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, in particular, with this person, he says, how can I equanimously or let go of the body while taking reasonable measures to protect it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, you can equanimously let go of the body by not holding on to it through your desires, through your intentional acts.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you're still... if your... if your behavior and speech is not purified,
[SPEAKER_00]: If that intentionality behind your actions is not discerned, you can wish all you want and theorize how to, you know, take control, how to be equanimous, what to do in this situation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Fundamentally, you're just managing the symptoms.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if the fear still overwhelms you, it's because the mind is still wilder than you were able to tame it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when such experiences come, well, the most you can do during those intense periods is don't make things worse through acts of body or speech.
[SPEAKER_00]: Mentally, as I said, try to try to endure these things on that level without, like, being filled with pressure and panic, like, I must get rid of this as soon as possible, because that's going to make it worse.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, when those episodes
[SPEAKER_01]: Subside, then you've got to start re-evaluating your whole life.
[SPEAKER_01]: Everything.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, what anxiety or fear shows you, it's not one little problem, just on that mundane level.
[SPEAKER_00]: It just reveals you the whole nature of your existence.
[SPEAKER_00]: The fact that you're liable to fear, the fact that you're liable to the mind turning against you, even if you did everything right, seemingly, in a worldly manner.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you really want to start re-evaluating your actions,
[SPEAKER_00]: Your ambitions, your aspirations, and yeah, then put everything down and see which one carries more worth to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if you are willingly, intentionally engaging with desires, act out of ill-will, careless in regard to your speech, do not bear that responsibility of your intentions and actions on that mental level, but
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't instantly want to psychologize, get rid of it, deal with it, so it doesn't bother you.
[SPEAKER_00]: You are enabling the wilderness of your mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: You are not really teaching it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not really conveying the message to the mind, so that it calms down.
[SPEAKER_01]: And with this, like, you know, fear of the uncertain...
[SPEAKER_00]: It was always uncertain.
[SPEAKER_00]: Things were not more uncertain today than they were yesterday, or the day you were born.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just that, under certain circumstances, you become more aware of the same uncertainty.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what you perceive.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, this is the bothersome aspect of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's really only because the threat of uncertainty can affect you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you still hold on to things, are established upon things, have appropriated things that are not in your control, that are subject to that uncertainty.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then, when uncertainty reveals itself,
[SPEAKER_00]: That's when you feel like, oh, you know, you are under a threat.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the whole, you know, the fundamental contemplations about sickness, aging, death, inevitability of change.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you want to be seeing and discerning whether there are things that you hold dear, that you are not questioning, that you're taking for granted, that would, that will be taken away by change when it occurs.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then basically let go of them before it happens.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's quite, yeah, it's quite difficult if you are... Well, usually, you're in a comfort zone and you're shielding yourself from that reality.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like only when sickness comes, you start realizing, oh, man... Well, that's what I'm saying.
[SPEAKER_00]: You actually, you want to start thinking about these things before these episodes occur, where, you know, you might have just enough room to not act out of the pressure when it gets too much.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're certainly not going to have enough
[SPEAKER_00]: Mental space to be able to maintain perspective and see through the origin and all these other things we talk about, because you just haven't been training it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, don't wait until you get sick.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't wait until you get sick, but start bringing up these contexts in a controlled manner on the basis of your virtue and sense restraint and taming of the senses and start recognizing value in that.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not going to be purified or perfected overnight, but that's not an excuse
[SPEAKER_00]: To dilute it as something to aspire for, or to even, like, completely dismiss it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like the... those... keeping the precepts, saying no to yourself, sense restraint.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like that gentle exposure to reality.
[SPEAKER_01]: To what's inevitable.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, no, exactly, yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what it does.
[SPEAKER_00]: Before it hits you in the face.
[SPEAKER_00]: Before it gets too much.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, before it gets too much.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the whole point of that whole training.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you know, you can do all the meditation calming you want, if you're not addressing the origin, the inadvertently fueled origins of the problem, fueled through your actions, all you're doing, as I said so many times before, it's like putting a plaster on a festering wound.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, nothing comes up.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Might look nice and clean and smell sterilized from the outside, but on the inside it's still much the same infection getting worse.